Okay בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, today's דף *daf* is קב *Kuf Bais*,
בבא קמא Bava Kamma *Bava Kamma* 102, and we pick up at
the very bottom of קא *Kuf Aleph* עמוד ב *amud bais*, and
we're in the middle of a discussion about קדושת שביעית *kedushas shvi’is*,
about what type of things have the sanctity of the שמיטה Shmita
*shmita* year, and the assumption initially would have been just foods, but
now the question is: maybe does that also apply to things that
are used for dyeing, or even to wood itself? And the גמרא's
Gemara *Gemara's* conclusion was that it is things like food, that הנאתו
וביעורו שוה *hana'aso u-viuro shaveh*, that you get the benefit from them
as they are being consumed. So that would include dyes. רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says that means because you use dyes when the dye gets
absorbed into the garment. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says when you wear the
garment you're a little bit wearing out the dye. But it does
not include firewood or just normal branches and wood, even when a
tree grows and a branch grows on שמיטה Shmita *shmita*, because that's
הנאה hana'ah, אחר ביעור *hana'as achar biuro*. It's only after something burns
initially and becomes like a type of a charcoal and becomes an
ember, that's really when you get the benefit from it, not when
it's at the moment of being consumed. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* questions this and it says like this: אמר קרא Amar
kra, *Amar krah*, we'll just pick up from there, third line from
the bottom, לאכלה le'ochla. *L’achlah*, so the שמיטה Shmita *shmita* should be
to you to eat, במי שהנאתו וביעורו שוין *b’mi she-hana'aso u-viuro shavin*,
things that are like food, that you benefit from it when it
is consumed. יצאו עצים *Yatzu eitzim*, this excludes normal types of woods
that would be used for firewood for cooking or for baking, שהנאה
אחר ביעורן *she-hana'as achar biuran*, that the benefit is after it is
consumed, because you want it to more be coals. But the גמרא
*Gemara* says: Well, that's not always true about all woods. והאיכא עצי
דמשחן דהנאתו וביעורו שוה
*Ve-ika eitzei d'mash'chan di-hana'aso u-viuro shaveh*? Isn't there woods of משחן *mash'chan*,
oily woods, that the benefit and their destruction is at the same
time? Now, what does this mean? רש"י *Rashi* says that it means
oily wood that is basically used for lighting and not
for making a fire to provide light, but it doesn't get burnt
up quickly and isn't used for cooking, and therefore that's exactly as
it's burning and providing light, you get the benefit at the same
time that it's being consumed. So it's a certain type of wood.
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says that it's not referring to a certain type
of wood, although the language sounds like that, but it's referring to
the question of how are you using it. If you're using it
to provide heat, or if you're using it for a certain type
of cooking as opposed to baking, then you actually don't want it
when it's an ember; you want it when it's a fire. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says: Isn't there a type of wood, or a
way you use wood, that the benefit comes at the time of
consumption, and therefore shouldn't that שמיטה Shmita *shmita* apply to that? So
אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, says רבא *Rava*, top of קב עמוד א
*Kuf Bais amud aleph*, סתם stam עצים להסקה הן עומדים *stam eitzim
l’hasakah hein omdim*. While that's true, the default use of wood is
for a fire, and let's say for a type of a baking
fire,
or a type of a fire that you would use that you
would want it after it becomes embers. And because that's the default,
that's what we're going to assume is the case when you have
wood that grows on שמיטה Shmita *shmita*. What does that mean exactly?
Why should that idea of סתם stam, עצים *stam eitzim* apply even
to a different type of wood? If רש"י *Rashi* is really talking
about a certain type of a species or whatever, then that would
sound like that סתם stam, *stam* is used just to provide light.
So the גמרא *Gemara* reads better like תוספות *Tosafot*, that the question
is what you're planning on using it for. And then it makes
a lot more sense. Since the default is you're going to use
them for a type of wood, since the default of firewood or
whatever is you're going to use it to get benefit after it
turns to embers, even if in your particular case you're using it
when the fire is still burning, nevertheless it never had קדושת שביעית
*kedushas shvi’is* to begin with. Okay, so that's the story. So we're
left still with a question: If there's wood that the סתם stam
*stam* would be to actually be הנאתו וביעורו שוה *hana'aso u-viuro shaveh*,
maybe it would have קדושת שביעית *kedushas shvi’is*, but when the סתם
stam. *stam* is not that way, then it does not have קדושת
שביעית *kedushas shvi’is*. Okay, now the גמרא *Gemara* continues, ועצים להסקה תנאי
היא *ve-eitzim l'hasakah tannai hi*, and wood used for making a fire
is a debate of תנאים *tannaim*. Now, what exactly this means is
not clear. Let's read how they're going to bring this debate of
תנאים *tannaim* into this question of wood made for fire. Let's read
the debate of תנאים *tannaim* and then we'll talk about what the
גמרא *Gemara* might mean by this framing statement. דתניא detanya, *D'tanya*, we
taught in the ברייתא braisa, *braitah*: אין In, משרין פירות שביעית לא
lo, למשרה ולא לכביסה *ein moshirin peirosh shvi'is lo l'mishrah ve-lo l'khvisah*.
רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yossi omer, נותנין פירות שביעית לתוך המשרה ולתוך
הכביסה *Rabbi Yosei omer nosnin peirosh shvi'is l'tokh ha-mishrah u-l'tokh ha-khvisah*. So
you cannot go ahead and use the produce of שמיטה *shmita*. רש"י
*Rashi* says, let's say we're talking about wine from שמיטה *shmita* grapes,
you cannot use it for soaking your flax in it or... for
laundering your clothing. I don't know why wine would work for laundering
your clothing, but whatever the case might be. And רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi allows you. So let's see what this debate is about.
מה טעמא דרבנן, Ma ta'ama deRabbanan, why did the Rabbis say you
can't? אמר קרא, amar kra, the פסוק posuk says, לאכלה ולא למשרה.
le'ochla velo lemishrah. It has to be for eating and not for
soaking your flax. לאכלה ולא לכבוסה, le'ochla velo lekhivusah, for eating and
not for doing laundry. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. אומר, and רבי Rebbi,
יוסי would say, אמר קרא, the פסוק posuk says, לכם, lakhem, it
should be for you, לכל צרכיכם, lekhol tsorkheikhem, you can use it
for all your uses. It's not limited just to things, just to
eat. ורבנן, Verabbanan, how would the Rabbis respond back to the לכם?
lakhem? נמי הכתיב לכם, Nami haktiv lakhem, doesn't it say לכם? lakhem?
No, לכם דומיא דלאכלה, lakhem dumya dele'ochla, במי שהנאתו וביעורו שוים. bemi
shehana'ato uvi'uro shavin.
So לכם lakhem is similar to לאכלה. le'ochla, Yes, לכם lakhem expands
לאכלה, le'ochla but it has to be similar to לאכלה le'ochla, and
something that you get the benefit when you actually consume it and
destroy it. So you can use שמיטה produce for more than just
food, but something where the הנאה, hana'ah, the benefit comes as it
is being destroyed. יצאו משרה וכבוסה, Yatsu mishrah ukhivusah, which excludes the
case of soaking and laundering, שהנאתן אחר ביעורן, shehana'atan akhar bi'uran, that
first they get the, the wine, let's use that example, gets absorbed
into the flax or into the garments and it only sort of
has the effect of doing what you want to the flax and
the garments, a while after, רש"י says if you're letting it soak
for a few days. So it's הנאתן אחר ביעורן. hana'atan akhar bi'uran.
So therefore שמיטה can only be used for things that are like
eating, that the הנאה, the benefit and the consumption come at the
same time. ולרבי יהודה נמי הכתיב לאכלה, UleRabbi Yehuda nami haktiv le'ochla,
so now according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, okay it says לכם
lakhem but לאכלה, le'ochla shouldn't לאכלה le'ochla limit it to some degree?
אמר לך, Amar lakh, he'll say back to you, ההוא מיבעי ליה
לכדתניא, hahu mibai leh likhedetanya, לאכלה le'ochla we need for what we
teach in a בריתא, Baraita, דתניא, we taught in the בריתא, Baraita,
לאכלה ולא למלוגמא. le'ochla velo lemlugma. So לאכלה le'ochla and not for
some type of a like a poultice, like some type of a
bandage, a salve or something that you would put on a wound.
Okay, so that you can't, you can't use it for that. So
why should we exclude it for that use but allow you to
use it for laundry and soaking your flax? So let's take a
look. ואתה אומר לאכלה ולא למלוגמא, Ve'atah omer le'ochla velo lemlugma, you're
saying that you can't use it for a poultice because that's not
like eating, או אינו אלא לאכלה ולא לכבוסה, o eino ela le'ochla
velo lekhivusah, maybe it means you can't use, also you shouldn't be
able to use it for like laundering? כשהוא אומר לכם, Keshehu omer
lakhem, no, לכם lakhem is a broadening word. הרי כבוסה אמור, Harei
khivusah amur, you're allowed to use it for laundering, you can make
it for all your uses. הא מה אני מקיים לאכלה, Ha mah
ani mekayem le'ochla, so how is לאכלה le'ochla limiting it? לאכלה ולא
למלוגמא, Le'ochla velo lemlugma, not for a poultice. So the בריתא Baraita
says here, מה ראית לרבות את הכבוסה ולהוציא את המלוגמא, mah ra'ita
lerabbot et hakhivusah ulehotzi et hamlugma, the obvious question, what's your principle
that your expansion of לאכלה le'ochla includes using it for laundry but
still excludes מלוגמא, mlugma, excludes this poultice?
מרבה אני את הכבוסה ששוה בכל אדם. Marbeh ani et hakhivusah sheshavah
bekhol adam. No, I'll include כבוסה khivusah which is something that everybody
has a use for. So
לכם lakhem is a common use that people have. Everybody needs to
launder clothing, I don't know about laundering it in wine, but whatever
the case might be, maybe it's white grapes, everybody needs to soak
their flax,
ומוציא אני את המלוגמא שאינו שוה בכל אדם. umotsi ani et hamlugma
she'eino shaveh bekhol adam. Okay, so that's sort of like what we
say by אכילה akhilah by יום טוב, Yom Tov, right? By אכילה
akhilah by יום טוב Yom Tov we sort of, the principle is
about דבר אשר יאכל לכל נפש, davar asher ye'akhel lekhol nefesh, דבר
השוה לכל נפש. davar hashaveh lekhol nefesh. So we're broadening it to
a type of a sense of a benefit that is common that
normal people need. So what we have here is a very interesting
debate between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the רבנן. Rabbanan. The רבנן
Rabbanan say that what can you use שמיטה for? שמיטה produce, לאכלה
le'ochla food, but in expansion of לאכלה le'ochla, similar to אכילה, akhilah,
things that הנאתן וביעורן שוה, hana'atan uvi'uran shaveh, that your benefit comes
when it's being consumed. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has a broader expansion
of לאכלה, le'ochla לאכלה le'ochla you can use it for anything that
is like אכילה akhilah that is a need that all people have,
a use that all people have, but not something that's only for
a small subset of people. And now the גמרא says, כמאן
אזלא הא דתניא, keman azla ha detanya, who's it going like the
בריתא Baraita that we teach, לאכלה ולא למלוגמא לאכמה ולא לזילוף? le'ochla
velo lemlugma le'akhma velo leziluf? It says לאכלה le'ochla so you can't
use שמיטה produce for a poultice and you can't use it for
like heating and you can't use it for like sprinkling wine to
like a, like an air
freshener, לאכלה ולא לעשות הימנו אפיקטויזין le'ochla velo la'asot himeno apiktevizyon and
not to make for it some type of a thing that would
cause you to throw up. So all those are seen as things
that some special people need, either because you're sick or because you're
finicky, but it's not a normal thing that people use. So כמאן?
keman? כרבי יוסי, keRabbi Yossi, that's going like רבי יוסי. It's only
excluding things that are not שוה לכל נפש. shaveh lekhol nefesh. דאי
כרבנן, De'i keRabbanan, if it was going like the Rabbis, איכא נמי
משרה וכבוסה, ika nami mishrah ukhivusah, it should have also excluded laundry
and soaking your flax. So that is the debate. לאכלה le'ochla. is
not limited to eating. How do we broaden it? Do we broaden
it one stage as the רבנן Rabbanan of only for things that
הנאתן וביעורן שוה, hana'atan uvi'uran shaveh, that your benefit comes when it's
being consumed? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has a broader expansion of לאכלה.
le'ochla לאכלה you can use it for anything that is like אכילה
akhilah that is a need that all people have, a use that
all people have, but not something that's only for a small subset
of people. Or do we go another stage which is רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda*, which is anything that is שווה לכל נפש
*shaveh l'chol nefesh*, that normal people need? And that's what תוספות *Tosafos*
says the tie-in is to עצים להסקה תנאי היא *eitzim l'hasaka tanai
hee*. Meaning, this question of whether firewood has קדושת שביעית *kedushas shvi'is*
is based on this debate of תנאים *Tannaim* of רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda. *Rebbi Yehuda* and the Rabbis. And it's very straightforward why, because
the same פסוק *posuk* that tells you לאכלה *l'achla* ולכם *u'lechem* of
what you can use שמיטה *shmita* produce for, that also should be
telling you what types of food, what type of produce has קדושת
שביעית *kedushas shvi'is*. If you can use שמיטה *shmita* produce for anything
that is fit to be eaten and fit for הנאה וביעורו שווה
*hana'ah u'biuro shaveh*, then the קדושת שביעית *kedushas shvi'is* applies to anything
that's הנאה וביעורו שווה *hana'ah u'biuro shaveh* that has benefit as it's
consumed, which means it would apply to dyes, but it would not
apply to wood. Whereas if you can use שמיטה *shmita* לאכלה *l'achla*
ולכם *u'lechem*, meaning you can use שמיטה *shmita*, the קדושת שמיטה *kedushas
shmita* allows it to be used for anything that is a common
use, שווה לכל נפש *shaveh l'chol nefesh*, therefore it applies to all
types of things that grow from the ground that is שווה לכל
נפש *shaveh l'chol nefesh* and it would apply to firewood as well.
So what קדושת שביעית *kedushas shvi'is* demands, be eaten and then other
things, הנאה וביעורו שווה *hana'ah u'biuro shaveh*, שווה לכל נפש *shaveh l'chol
nefesh*, apologies for that. So what קדושת שמיטה *kedushas shmita* demands, what
you must do, the קדושה *kedusha* says you must do with the
fruit, you must eat it, or you must get benefit as you're
consuming it, or any type of benefit that is common to everyone,
what it demands also says to what that it applies to, the
type of produce that is made for that purpose, made to be
eaten, or made for הנאה וביעור שווה *hana'ah u'biur shaveh*, or made
for benefit of שווה לכל נפש *shaveh l'chol nefesh*. And therefore whether
it applies to firewood is exactly dependent on that debate. Okay, now
we go back to the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* at the two dots.
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda? אומר אם השבח יתר על היציאה *Rebbi Yehuda
omer im hashvach yeser al hayetzi'ah*. Okay, so here's a case where
the dyer applied the wrong dye, red or black or whatever. רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir, *Rebbi Meir* says, you know, שינוי קונה shinuy koneh.
*shinui koneh*, and that the dyer now because he made it different
from what the person wanted, he now owns the wool and he
has to pay the owner for the cost of the wool, where
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda* says שינוי shinuy *shinui* is not
קונה koneh, *koneh*, or at least maybe we'll say a שינוי shinuy
*shinui* in this type of a context where it was a mistake
and you weren't trying to steal it, you're not קונה koneh, *koneh*
and it's still the original owner's wool. But because you the dyer
made a mistake and that wasn't what he wanted, so he has
the upper hand. And he'll pay you for either your expenses, not
your labor, but your material
expenses, and if you ever get your car fixed, parts, labor is
a very big piece of that bill. So either he'll pay you
for the parts,
the expenses, but not the labor, or for the amount in which
the value of the wool increased, whichever is less. That's רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda, *Rebbi Yehuda*'s position. Okay, now let's take a look at
the גמרא *Gemara*. יתיב רב יוסף Rav Yosef אחורי דרב אבא קמיה
דרב הונא *Yasiv Rav Yosef achorei d'Rav Abba kamei d'Rav Huna*. So
רב יוסף Rav Yosef *Rav Yosef* and רב אבא *Rav Abba* were
both hearing a שיעור *shiur* from רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna*.
ויתיב רב הונא Rav Huna וקאמר *Veyasiv Rav Huna veka'amar*, and רב
הונא *Rav Huna* was sitting and saying הלכה halacha. כרבי יהושע בן
קרחה *halacha k'Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha*, we rule like רבי יהושע בן
קרחה *Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha*, we'll see in which case in a
minute. והלכה כרבי יהודה Yehuda. *Vehalacha k'Rebbi Yehuda*, and we rule like
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rebbi Yehuda*, which is our רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda. *Rebbi Yehuda*. אדרינהו רב יוסף לאפיה *Adrinei Rav Yosef l'apei*, so
רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* turned his face away from רב הונא *Rav
Huna*. He did not agree with what רב הונא *Rav Huna* was
saying. אמר *Amar* he said, בשלמא רבי יהושע בן קרחה איצטריך *bishlama
Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha itztrich*, I understand that you're saying we rule
like רבי יהושע בן קרחה *Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha*, we'll again we'll
see which one in a minute. אעלה על דעתך אמינא יחיד ורבים
הלכה כרבים *Asalkasaitach amina
yachid verabbim halacha k'rabbim*,
that normally he's a דעת יחיד *das yachid* in whichever debate we're
talking about, and we would normally think like you go by the
majority. קמשמע לן הלכה כיחיד *Kamashmalan halacha k'yachid*, so there you're telling
me in this case we rule like the minority opinion. Now before
we get on to understanding the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda*
thing which upset him, let's figure out what this רבי יהושע בן
קרחה *Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha* is. רבי יהושע בן קרחה מאי *Rebbi
Yehoshua ben Korcha mai*? What's this teaching of רבי יהושע בן קרחה
*Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha*? דתניא *Detanya* we taught in the ברייתא braisa,
*Baraisa*: רבי יהושע בן קרחה אומר *Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha omer*, מלוה
בשטר אינו נפרע מהם מלוה על פה נפרע מהם מפני שהוא כמציל
מידם *Milveh beshtar eini nifra meihem milveh al peh nifra meihem mipnei
shehu k'matzil miyadam*. So you're not allowed to do business with non-Jews
or with pagans, whatever, idol worshippers three days before their holidays, but
and doing business includes getting your loans paid from them, paying back
your loans, getting your loans paid from them. And רבי יהושע בן
קרחה *Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha* makes a distinction. He says if you've
got documentation, it's a מלוה בשטר *milveh beshtar*, then you don't get
it paid back during these three days before because you'll always be
able to prove it in court and get it paid back later.
But if it's only an oral loan and you have no evidence
and therefore it's at risk and you have an opportunity now to
get it paid back, then you can collect because it is מציל
מידם *matzil miyadam*, you're saving that money from their hands, that money
might get lost. And therefore I will allow you to collect even
right before their holiday. Okay, so that is a דעת יחיד *das
yachid* but we פוסקים *pasken* that way. אלא הלכה כרבי יהודה למה
לי *Ella halacha k'Rebbi Yehuda lama lee*? Why do you have to
rule like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda* of our משנה Mishna
*Mishnah*? סתם משנה. stam Mishna, מחלוקת ואחריה סתם היא! Machlokes v'acharei stam
hi! It's a debate in our משנה Mishna between רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda. and רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir but it's followed by a סתם
משנה, stam Mishna and we'll see the סתם משנה stam Mishna in
a minute, and ומחלוקת ואחריה סתם הלכה כסתם Umachlokes v'acharei stam halacha
k'stam and our general ruling is that if you have a debate
in one משנה Mishna. and a סתם stam that occurs, you know,
an anonymous משנה Mishna that does not mention the debate and anonymously
goes by one opinion, you go by the anonymous משנה. Mishna. And
how is that this case? מחלוקת בבבא קמא, Machlokes b'Bava Kamma,
the debate is here in our משנה Mishna. בבבא קמא, b'Bava Kamma,
צמר לבן וצבעו שחור שחור וצבעו אדום, tzemer lavan utzvo shachor, shachor
utzvo adom,
so he red or he did black, you want a black he
did red, רבי מאיר אומר נותן לו דמי צמרו, Rebbi Meir omer
nosein lo d'mei tzmoro, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that you pay
him for the wool and you the dyer keep the wool, רבי
יהודה אומר אם השבח יתר על היציאה נותן לו את היציאה ואם
היציאה יתירה על השבח נותן לו את השבח. Rebbi Yehuda omer im
hashevach yaser al hayetzia nosein lo es hayetzia v'im hayetzia yeseira al
hashevach nosein lo es hashevach. You pay him whichever is less, the
increased value of the wool or his expenses. Okay
so that's the debate, וסתם בבבא מציעא, v'stam b'Bava Metzia, and then
in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia we have a סתם stam משנה mishna,
that says just teach it straight like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda, דתנן
כל המשנה ידו על התחתונה, Detnan kol hamishaneh yado al hatachtona,
anybody who switches and meaning in this type of a case like
you have a craftsman, a you know, that did different than what
he was told to do, he has the lower hand. So the
owner has the upper hand and that would mean can demand will
have the right to pay the lesser of the benefit or the
or the expenses. וכל החוזר בו ידו על התחתונה, V'chol hachozer bo
yado al hatachtona,
and if somebody backs out of a contract, then the other side
has the upper hand. And that's anyways but the first clause is
definitely seen to apply to the case of our משנה. So why
did you have to פסקן הלכה כרבי יהודה? pasken halacha k'Rebbi Yehuda?
It's obvious, that's a later משנה. Okay, that's anonymous that way. ורב
הונא, v'Rav Huna, so why did רב הונא feel you needed to
פסקן pasken like רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda איצטריכא, Itztricha, he needed it.
סלקא דעתך אמינא אין סדר למשנה, Salaka dach'tach amina ein seder lamishna,
I would have thought that maybe we say there's no particular order
to the משניות. mishnayos. You can't infer anything from the order, right?
Maybe they were originally taught in a different order, even though obviously
they were eventually organized by רבי, but maybe you can't infer something
like it didn't they weren't taught chronologically. So therefore the idea of
which is first and which is last is not really a meaningful
statement, okay. אין סדר למשנה. Ein seder lamishna. וסתם ואחר כך מחלוקת
היא, V'stam v'achar kach machlokes hi, maybe it's the reverse. Maybe if
we're thinking chronologically, the סתם, stam you know, preceded the debate. Alright,
ורב יוסף, v'Rav Yosef, רב יוסף would say back, אי הכי, ei
hachi, if that's true, כל מחלוקת ואחר כך סתם נימא אין סדר
למשנה, kol machlokes v'achar kach stam neima ein seder lamishna, then you
how can you say that? Every time we say it's a מחלוקת
machlokes and then a סתם, say how do you know what the
order is, right? Maybe it was taught in the opposite order. You
can't infer anything from the order. Yeah we have a principle of
מחלוקת ואחר כך סתם, machlokes v'achar kach stam, according to you that
principle could never be applied. נימא
אין סדר למשנה Neima ein seder lamishna וסתם ואחר כך מחלוקת היא.
v'stam v'achar kach machlokes hi. Let's say every סתם followed by a
מחלוקת machlokes might be a מחלוקת machlokes and then a סתם. ורב
הונא, v'Rav Huna, now רב הונא would say back: No. כי לא
אמרינן אין סדר למשנה, Ki lo amrinan ein seder lamishna, I don't
mean obviously there's never an order. I mean, when do I mean
there's not an order, it's a double negative, when would I concede
that there is an order? בחדא מסכתא, B'chada masechta, in one מסכת.
masechet. Okay, in one מסכת masechet we think that, you know, maybe
we're again רבי יהודה organized it in a meaningful way and if
he had a debate taught earlier and a סתם later, he meant
to say this סתם now is the consensus or is the הלכתא
halachic opinion. There we can say within one מסכת masechet it's ordered
in a meaningful way. אבל
בתרי מסכתא, Aval bitrei masechta, but in two מסכתות, masechtos, בבא קמא
ובבא מציעא, Bava Kamma u'Bava Metzia, אמרינן, amrinan, then we would say
that there's no order. Okay so you can't infer something. Each מסכת
masechet is like a, you know, is like an entity onto itself
and you can't infer something from something that appears in one מסכת
masechet and something in another, which is first and which is last.
Within a מסכת, masechet, that's one entity and there the order matters.
Okay, so that's that makes a lot of sense. So what why
what would רב יוסף say back that he considers it a סתם
אחר כך מחלוקת? stam achar kach machlokes?
ורב יוסף, V'Rav Yosef, he would say, כולה נזיקין חדא מסכתא היא.
kula nezikin chada masechta hi. Okay, but you know, all of נזיקין
Nezikin is really one מסכת. masechet. The reason it's called בבא Bavas.
קמא First Gate, Middle Gate, Last Gate, is because נזיקין Nezikin originally
was thirty פרקים prakim long and that's way too big for a
מסכת, masechet, so we divide it into first third, middle third, and
last third. And you know what? מסכת כלים Masechet Keilim in טהרות
Taharos is also thirty פרקים prakim long and it is בבא קמא,
בבא מציעא ובבא בתרא. Bava Kamma, Bava Metzia u'Bava Basra. So really
that is conceptually one big thing and you can order is meaningful
throughout those three בבא. אי נמי, Ei nami, ואי בעית אימא, v'ei
bayis eima, if you want I'll say, משום דקתני לגבי הלכתא פסיקתא.
mishum d'katani lgabei hilchasa pesikta. It's not just because it's סתם במחלוקת
ואחר כך סתם stam b'machlokes v'achar kach stam that he felt it
was obvious we rule like רבי יהודה, but because it's taught in
a list of things that are like categorical statements. כל המשנה ידו
על התחתונה וכל החוזר בו ידו על התחתונה. Kol hamishaneh yado al
hatachtona v'chol hachozer bo yado al hatachtona. Whoever, you know, whoever does
something, you know, in the wrong way, he has the lower hand,
whoever backs out of a contract, he has the lower hands. These
are seen as certain like categorical statements and they're not just a
normal סתם and therefore it seems to be like
this is accepted. הלכה. So he says you didn't need to פסקן
pasken like יהודה. Either way it's clear we rule like רב יהודה.
Reb Yehuda. Now, as I said, you know, the גמרא sometimes frames
the debate in רש״י Rashi about רב יהודה Reb Yehuda and רב
מאיר Reb Meir whether שינוי shinuy is קונה, koneh but we rule
normally שינוי shinuy, is קונה, koneh, and here we rule like רב
יהודה Reb Yehuda that it's not like you keep the wool, it's
the original owner keeps the wool and just figures out what to
pay you. So it probably so what we're saying here שינוי shinuy
is not קונה koneh means in this case, not about somebody who's
a גזלן gazlan and then did a שינוי, shinuy but you know
you were a worker, you were trying to do the right thing,
you accidentally did the wrong thing, that is not enough to make
you now take possession of that object. It still belongs to the
original owner and we have to figure out now what the owner
is going to pay. Okay, תנו רבנן, tana rabanan, last line on
ק״ב עמוד א׳. kuf bet amud aleph.
הנותן מעות לשלוחו, hanosein maos leshlucho, somebody gives money to his messenger
ליקח לו חטים ולקח מהם שעורים likach lo chittin velakach mehem seorin
to purchase wheat and instead he purchases barley. Now, we're going to
see that we're talking about a case where you're actually doing this
not because you're sending somebody to the store because you're making bread,
but because you are actually you are trying to invest. It's a
business deal. You're doing it as product and you're going to buy
it and resell it. So you had told him to buy wheat
and instead he buys barley. שעורים ולקח מהם חטים seorin velakach mehem
chittin or the reverse. תניא חדא, tanya chada, we teach one ברייתא,
braita. אם פיחתו פיחתו לו ואם הותירו הותירו לו, im pichasu pichasu
lo veim hosiru hosiru lo, that basically the person that you made
that switched from what you said, did barley instead of wheat or
whatever, he basically now owns the barley or the wheat. And if
the barley or the wheat if it goes down in value, he
suffers the loss. If it goes up in value, he gets the
gain. He has to pay you for whatever like if you advanced
him the money or you gave him the money to purchase for
you, he's got to repay you whatever money the amount of the
money it was, but it's his barley or it's his wheat, he
changed from what you said. Okay, that's one opinion. ותניא חדא, vetanya
chada, we taught another ברייתא,
אם פיחתו פיחתו לו ואם הותירו הותירו לאמצע. im pichasu pichasu lo
veim hosiru hosiru laemsa. No, it sort of split. If it goes
down in value, he suffers the loss. If it goes up in
value, then you split it. Now what sense does that make? So
it seems that the case was one in which had he done
the right thing, the deal was you go, you buy the wheat,
you buy the barley, it's my money, but you're doing the effort,
maybe you're also going to resell it, okay, and what we'll do
is we'll split the profits and we'll split the loss. Okay, I
contribute the money, you contribute the effort, we split the profits, we
split the loss. That would be if it was sort of normally
done that way. Some people might be thinking that sounds a little
like ריבית, ribbis, but no, since he's also going to split the
loss, it's not like ריבית. ribbis. ריבית ribbis is when the בעל
הבית baal habayis is assured the principal. Okay, so that's normally how
it would be, but because this guy did the wrong thing, let's
say I was the one who was investing the money, I'm not
going to let his mistake hurt me. So if he bought barley
and now it's going down in value and I wanted him to
buy wheat, it was his mistake, he's got to suffer the loss.
However, since in the end it was my money and he did
purchase it for me and all of that, if it goes up
in value, we'll go by original agreement that then we will actually
split the profit. And that's what will happen. Now I should pause
for a minute and just say, before we go on to analyze
this any further, that this actually is like a great deal for
the guy who gives the money, and it's almost sort of like
it could be a way of actually getting interest for your money.
You go ahead and you give, you know, a thousand dollars to
a person and he goes ahead and buys something different than what
you told him to do. Okay, in that case,
what will happen?
He, if it goes down in value what he bought, that's his
loss, but you still have the right, you know, to get back
the value of your money. So your investment is secured because any
loss of principal he suffers and you don't suffer. But any profit,
you actually get half the profit. So here's a way that you're
giving your money, your principal is secured, and you're going to get
if you might not necessarily get it if it doesn't turn a
profit, but if it does turn a profit, you will get profit
with a secure principal. So this might be a sort of roundabout
way to arrange for a certain type of, you know, charging interest.
And תוספות actually says that. תוספות actually points out that according to
this, you could sort of do it with a wink and a
nod and you could go ahead and say to somebody: "Okay, here's
ten thousand dollars. I want you to lend this money out for
me, let's say, let's say lend it out to non-Jews and charge
them interest or
whatever, but I'm only allowing you to do it if you put
it in like the Brinks
safe in a huge careful, you know, safe that's like cost you
ten thousand dollars, super secure, and I'm only letting you do it
if you make sure that you get gold and silver as collateral."
And that's all sort of said with like a wink and a
nod. Now this guy's going to go ahead and he's going to
lend out the money and get interest and he's not going to
follow those instructions. So what's that going to mean? That's going to
mean that I am going to be able to get half of
the profit, okay, with my principal secure. And so it's an interesting
way this penalty here actually creates a nice little workaround and a
loophole. Anyway, that's what we have here according to the second ברייתא.
Now let's understand what this debate is about. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar
Rabbi Yochanan said רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: לא קשיא, lo kashya, הא
רבי מאיר והא רבי יהודה. ha Rabbi Meir ve-ha Rabbi Yehuda. It's
the debate between רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה. Our רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה. הא רבי מאיר דאמר שינוי קונה,
Ha Rabbi Meir d'amar shinuy koneh, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says
שינוי קונה. shinuy koneh So now this is different, this is not
you're doing a שינוי shinuy on the object and you're putting red
dye rather than black dye, okay, but what you're doing is you're
changing from the instructions of the בעל הבית. balabayas. So once you
change from the instructions and you bought barley instead of wheat, it
now becomes your money, your loss, your profit, it's all yours. Obviously
you have to pay back the original money, just like our משנה,
pay back the wool, it's all yours, okay, when you change from
the instructions of the בעל הבית. balabayas. והא רבי יהודה Ve-ha Rabbi
Yehuda and the other position is רבי יהודה דאמר שינוי אינו קונה
d'amar shinuy eino koneh that yes you change from the instructions, but
it's still his money, it's still his wheat or his barley. Again,
because you made a mistake, you're going to suffer the loss, but
it's still his, and therefore you will continue to split the profit
as the original deal was. That's רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. מתקיף
לה רב אלעזר Matkif la Rav Elazar רב אלעזר Rav Elazar challenges:
ממאי, mimai, who says that's what's going on? דילמא עד כאן לא
קאמר רבי מאיר אלא במידי דחזי ליה לגופיה. Dilma ad kan lo
ka'amar Rabbi Meir ela be-midi de-chazi lei le-gufeh. Maybe רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir only said, you know, this idea that שינוי קונה shinuy koneh.
when it is something you were planning on using for yourself. You
wanted, you know, a red wool because you were going to make
yourself a red garment or a black garment, you know, so it
was something that you personally cared whether it was red or black
or how it was done. And therefore when you go against that,
שינוי קונה. אבל לסחורה, Aval l'schora,
but if you're doing it for trade, לא אמר, lo amar, he
wouldn't have said it, because you know, then it's all product. What
do I care really if it's barley or wheat? I only care
if it turns a profit. Now okay, but you might care barley
or wheat because you think one of them is going to turn
a profit more than the other. But what he's claiming is that
maybe for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. this idea of that you really
violated and it becomes yours is much more
when the particulars really matter, not when you're just seeing it as
product, okay, and if it's a product, then fine, it's not enough
of a violation to that it becomes, you know, the שליח's, shliach's,
it's still yours, it doesn't become the one who changed it, but
again, he will suffer any loss. אלא אמר רב אלעזר, Ela amar
Rav Elazar, oh so if you can say that then we can
have both of these cases going like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir ולא
קשיא, Ve-lo kashya, כאן לאכילה כאן לסחורה. kan l'chila kan l'schora. Okay,
if you're sending your שליח shliach to buy wheat and he buys
barley or the reverse because you actually want to make bread, then
if he violates what you said, according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
that's like the red and the black and so on, and it's
now his money, his wheat, his barley and he has to pay
you back the money. However, if you're sending him to do it
for an investment, in that case since for you it's all just
product, as long as he will suffer any of the loss because
he didn't listen to you, you're totally okay, you know, then it's
still enough that it's yours and you will still get half of
the profit. Okay, so that's the debate, or that's the two ways
of explaining it, a debate of רבי יהודה and רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir. or within רבי מאיר. גחכו עלה במערבא לרבי יוחנן, Gachachu ala
b'ma'arava l'Rabbi Yochanan,
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they laughed about רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's
position. Now that's pretty funny because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is from
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Normally it's somebody says something in בבל Bavel
and they laugh about it in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Anyway, they
laughed about this about רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's position in ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, אליבא דרבי יהודה, aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda, based on רבי יהודה.
Because רבי יהודה, remember, what was his idea? His idea was for
רבי יהודה שינוי is not קונה, here again שינוי not meaning a
change in the object but going against instructions. So the שליח shliach
bought barley instead of wheat, even though he went against instructions,
the money still belongs to the בעל הבית, balabayas, and therefore, you
know, the barley belongs to the בעל הבית balabayas with the provision
that the שליח shliach because he messed up will suffer any loss,
okay. But he says one minute, I don't get it, וכי מי
הודיע לבעל חטים שיקנה חטים לבעל מעות. ve-chi mi odia l'ba'al chitim
she-yakneh chitim l'ba'al ma'ot. Since this guy, the שליח, shliach, is not
following the instructions of the בעל הבית, balabayas,
so when the owner of the wheat, let's say he was told
to get barley and he gets wheat, when the owner of the
wheat is giving it to the שליח, shliach, okay, the שליח shliach
is not operating according to the wishes of the בעל הבית. balabayas.
So you know,
how is the בעל הבית balabayas being קונה the wheat? The שליח
shliach isn't representing him
and the owner of the wheat isn't intending that it should be
owned to the בעל הבית, balabayas, he only sees the שליח shliach
in front of him. So how does this happen? I get that
it's not like he stole the money or whatever, but since he's
not representing him, I still don't get how the בעל הבית balabayas
winds up owning the wheat. Okay, that's what he asks. Since you
know the בעל הבית balabayas is still going to get half the
profits as we've been saying, it's clear that the בעל הבית balabayas
does own it with It is a violation of the will of
the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis*. That's why he said it's a debate
of רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* and רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. What do
you do about a case of a major violation? And once it's
a major violation of the will of the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis*,
then how is it that he's seen as a שליח shaliach *shaliach*
and how does the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis* get ownership of this
wheat? But רש"י *Rashi* points out that this is particularly sharp according
to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, right, because for רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
it really is a real violation of the will of the בעל
הבית *ba'al habayis*. That's why he said it's a debate of רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* and רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. What do you do
about a case of a major violation? And once it's a major
violation of the will of the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis*, then how
is it that he's seen as a שליח *shaliach* and how does
the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis* get ownership of this wheat? But רש"י
*Rashi* says, but according to ר' אלעזר *Rebbi Elazar*, remember ר' אלעזר
*Rebbi Elazar* said, no, even רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* would agree it's
all just product. So if it's all just product, it's not a
big violation really, then we can say that he still represents the
בעל הבית *ba'al habayis*. But for רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, if it
is a real violation, and that's why רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says
that it's a שינוי *shinuy*, then how can רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
say that the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis* owns it? The שליח *shaliach*
is not representing the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis* by buying wheat instead
of buying barley. Okay, מסקיף לה רב שמואל בר ססרטי *Maskif la
Rav Shmuel bar Sasrati*. So before we answer, we're going to answer
a question with another question. מסקיף לה רב שמואל בר ססרטי
*Maskif la Rav Shmuel bar Sasrati* challenged this question. אי הכי אפילו
חיטים וחיטים נמי לא *Ee hachi afilu chitin v'chitin nami lo*. So
if that's true, then the guy who's selling—the answer's going to be
obvious—when this שליח *shaliach* comes to buy the wheat, the seller doesn't
know that ראובן *Reuven* sent the שליח *shaliach*. He just sees the
שליח *shaliach* in front of him. So how does ראובן *Reuven* wind
up owning the wheat, even if the guy is doing exactly what
he was asked? So אמר רבי אבהו *Amar Rabbi Abbahu*, no, that's
obvious. שאני חיטים וחיטים דשליחותיה קא עביד *Shani chitin v'chitin d'shlichusei ka
avid*, וכי בעל הבית דמי *ve'chi ba'al habayis dami*. No, no, no,
as long as the שליח *shaliach* is doing what he was told,
then it doesn't matter, the seller thinks he's selling it to the
שליח *shaliach*, but the שליח *shaliach* represents the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis*.
That we get. But once you're saying it's a שינוי *shinuy* and
the
שליח *shaliach* is a משנה *mishaneh* and all of that, then how
can he be representing the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis* and how does
the wheat get owned by the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis*? תדע *Teda*,
now I'll show you that that's true, that we say that you
represent, even if the guy doesn't know who you're representing. דתנן *Detnan*,
we taught in the משנה *Mishnah*, as long as you're doing the
שליחות *shlichus*, אחד המקדיש נכסיו Hamakdish nechasav, ואחד המעריך את עצמו אין
לו בכסות אשתו ולא בכסות בניו ולא בצבע שצבע לשמן *echad hamakdish
nechasav v'echad hama'arich es atzmo ein lo b'chesus ishto v'lo b'chesus banav
v'lo b'tzeva shetzava lishmon*. Okay, so somebody went ahead and he said
all my property I'm giving to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis
Hamikdash*. Or he said my value I am dedicating to the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*. And now, so in the first case,
you have to figure out all of his property. You look at
all of his property and you take a moving van and you
schlepp it away. Even when he says I owe a thousand dollars
to the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, you have to go and see
if he doesn't have that money in cash, you go see what
property he has to collect from. So you can collect from all
of
his—so certainly let's focus on the first case. You really schlepp away
all his property. But here's what he's not sanctifying.
The clothing, his wife's clothing, that's not included in his הקדש hekdesh
*hekdesh*, and his children's clothing, and
if he bought some dye and he dyed their clothing or whatever,
ולא בסנדלים חדשים שלקחן לשמן *v'lo b'sandalim chadashim shelakchan lishmon*. So if
he's buying dye or if he's buying sandals, all those things, even
if he hasn't given it to them yet, they are not included
when he says I'm sanctifying them. Now, the point is, one minute,
if he hasn't given them the sandals yet, let's look at the
sandals case, then
why isn't that sanctified? He said all my property, and he hasn't
given it to them yet. ואמאי לימא המוכר נמי מידע ידע דלצבע
שצבעו לאשתו *Ve'amai leima hamocher nami meyda yada d'letzeva shetzav'o l'ishto*. So
it talks about the case of the dye, but the sandals is
the easier one. Who said, if he said, "Hey, go ahead and
dye this garment for me red," and he didn't tell the dyer
that it was his wife's garment, or he bought sandals, so it
doesn't belong to the wife yet. He hasn't—the dyer or the guy
selling the sandals didn't know that it was for the wife and
didn't have intent to transfer to the wife, and nevertheless it sounds
like it already belongs to the wife and the הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*
doesn't apply to it. אלא לאו משום דאמרינן דשליחותיה קא עביד *Ella
lav mishum d'amrinan d'shlichusei ka avid*. It must be that even though
the dyer doesn't know and the shoe seller doesn't know, the husband
is representing his wife even though she didn't appoint him. He's doing
her a benefit, that's the idea of זכין *zachin*. He's representing his
wife and even as—by representing his wife and doing what—therefore it's acquired
by her. וכי יד אשה דמי *V'chi yad isha dami*, he's like
an extension of his wife. הכא נמי שליחותיה קא עביד וכי יד
בעל הבית דמי *Hacha nami shlichusei ka avid ve'chi yad ba'al habayis
dami*. And therefore the same would be true. As long as the
שליח *shaliach* is doing what he was told, then the seller doesn't
have to know that he's serving as an agent. It's just he
is in his capacity an extension of the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis*
and the wheat goes to him. But once he does something that
is considered a שינוי *shinuy*, okay, so much that רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* would say that he's קונה *koneh* and it breaks it completely,
then the גמרא *Gemara* says even if for רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
he's not קונה *koneh* the money or the wheat or whatever, how
is it that he represents the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis* and this
wheat now is owned by the בעל הבית *ba'al
habayis*? So and so and but we don't have a problem when
he's doing what he was told to do because then he clearly
is an extension. So, we're not done with this. אמר רבי אבא,
לא, that's not a proof. That case of the guy buying the
sandals for his wife is not a proof that when the שליח
is doing it, he
automatically works even if you don't inform the seller. Why? How else
would you explain it? כל המקדש נכסיו אין דעתו על כסות אשתו
ובניו. Kol hamakdish nechasav ein daato al ksus ishto uvanav. It could
be that the sandals still don't belong to his wife yet because
he hasn't brought them home yet to give it to his wife.
And nevertheless, the הקדש hekdesh. doesn't apply to the sandals because even
though he says "all my property," he's not thinking about the stuff
that his wife owns or that he intends to give to his
wife. That's not what he is intending. So you really can't prove
from here that he purchased it for that his wife owns it,
you know, without the seller knowing, because it might just be he
wasn't intending to include it in his הקדש, hekdesh, even if the
wife didn't own it.
So מתקיף לה רבי זירא. Maskif lah Rebbi Zeira. רבי זירא Rebbi
Zeira challenged that challenge. וכי דעתו של אדם על תפיליו? Vechi daato
shel adam al tefillav? No, what do we care whether he was
thinking about it or not thinking about it? If he says "I'm
sanctifying all my property," do you think he wanted to sanctify his
תפילין? tefillin? Presumably not, okay?
ותנן, Vetnan, המקדיש נכסיו, if somebody sanctifies all their property,
מעלין לו תפילין. maalin lo tefillin. You basically, you know, assess the
value of the תפילין tefillin and you make him redeem the תפילין
tefillin and you give the money to the בית המקדש so that
he can keep on wearing the תפילין. tefillin. But what you see
is he sanctified the תפילין. tefillin. So clearly, once you say "all
my property," we take you literally even if you would have wanted
to or not wanted to. So clearly yes, his wife must own
those sandals already. אמר ליה אביי, Amar leh Abaye, אביי Abaye still
resists. אין, yes, דעתו של אדם על תפיליו. daato shel adam al
tefillav. When he says "all my property," he is still thinking about
his תפילין, tefillin, he's thinking about
everything, okay?
המקדיש נכסיו סבר מצוה קא עבידנא. Hamakdish nechasav savar mitzvah ka avidna.
If you're sanctifying your property, you think, look, I'm doing a מצוה.
mitzvah. Okay, I'm doing a מצוה, mitzvah, so it's okay, my תפילין
tefillin also. Okay, that that you don't think to exclude it. ואין
דעתו של אדם על כסות אשתו ובניו. Ve-ein daato shel adam al
ksus ishto uvanav. But you don't, but even in that case, you
mean to exclude, you know, the clothing of your wife and children,
or even the clothing intended for them. Why? Why would that be
more clearly excluded? משום איבה, Mishum eivah, for hatred, okay? You don't
want your wife and children yelling at you that you're stripping them
and their closets and giving it away to הקדש. hekdesh So, you
know, if it's between you and God and you're giving your תפילין
tefillin to הקדש, you know, you figure okay, I'm doing a מצוה,
mitzvah, God will understand. And anyway, we make you redeem it. Okay,
but clearly, you know, you're thinking about you don't want to get
yelled at from, you know, your wife or children, so clearly you
are not planning on doing anything that's going to get you into
trouble, okay? And therefore, you do not include stuff that belongs to
them or that is going to them. And therefore, you can't prove
from this that this idea that even if the store owner doesn't
know and the seller doesn't know, it goes to the person you're
representing.
So, we're still not done. מתקיף לה רב אושעיא. Maskif lah Rav
Oshaya. רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya challenged. That can work that you don't
mean that you mean to exclude or you don't mean to include
stuff that's going to your wife in the first case, when you
sanctify the property. ולא חייבי ערכין שנו כאן? Velo chayavei arachin shanu
kan? But there were two cases about excluding the wife's clothing. One
case was you sanctified, the other was you just
accepted your ערך, erech, you know, your value, whatever, a thousand dollars
to the בית המקדש. And then the בית דין Beis Din is
going to come and see what property they can collect from. So
that is against your will. That has nothing to do with what
you sanctified. That is the בית דין Beis Din coming and showing
up and seizing property. And therefore, it's a question, it's a strict
question of who owns the property, you or your
wife? ותנן, Vetnan, חייבי ערכין ממשכנין אותן. Chayavei arachin memashkenin osan. That
when
people owe money for an ערך, erech, you go ahead and you
seize their property as collateral. וכי דעתו של אדם על עצמו למשכנו?
Vechi daato shel adam al atzmo lemashkeno? And now clearly, you don't
want your property seized as collateral, but it doesn't matter, okay? You
wanted to give a thousand dollars, and if you don't have the
money, they're going to seize it against your will. We don't care
what you want or don't want. And nevertheless, they can't take the
stuff that's going for your wife. All right? So you see that
it seems like good evidence that even without the store owner knowing,
if you represent somebody, it goes to that person. But no, we're
going to push it off one final time. אלא אמר רבי אבא,
Ela amar Rebbi Abba, כל המקדיש נכסיו נעשה כמי שהקנה להן כסות
אשתו ובניו מעיקרא. Kol hamakdish nechasav naaseh k'mi shehikneh lahen ksus ishto
uvanav me-ikara. When you are about to sanctify your property, and presumably
this also means when you're about to accept some הקדש debt upon
yourself, okay, you in your mind, again, because you don't want to
get yelled at, you in your mind are... it's as if, meaning
probably חז"ל Chazal made it as if, okay, because what you would
want is. is to keep their property off limits. So therefore you
stuff that is going to them, it's like you've already transferred it
to them and that took place before you were מקדיש *makdish* or
before you put yourself in a situation where the בית המקדש *Beis
HaMikdash* could come and take collateral. And it's נעשה כמי *na'aseh k'mi*
means חז"ל *Chazal* treat it as if because that's what we need
to do in order to make society run smoothly, we treat it
as if that transfer occurred. So basically what it's saying is that
case of הקדש *hekdesh* is an exception. Okay, yes, it's true maybe
we could say the wife does not own those sandals that you
bought for her in principle but because of that special case of
מקדיש *makdish*, we're going to make it as if she does own
it. But as a general rule we have yet to prove that
just because you're representing your משלח *meshaleach*, you're representing the one who
sent you, that that property that the seller, you know, if he
doesn't know that you're representing that person, we still have a big
question mark whether actually that property transfers to the original, to the
person sending it to you. Okay, so just to repeat and we'll
end for here today, according to the question is according to רבי
יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* that it's really considered according to you know רבי
יוחנן
*Rebbe Yochanan* that sees this as a debate of רבי יהודה *Rebbe
Yehuda* and רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir* that buying wheat as opposed to
barley is a real שינוי *shinui* and for רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir*
you're קונה *koneh* and for רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* you're not קונה
*koneh*, so okay we said you're not קונה *koneh* but it still
belongs to the person who sent it to you,
who sent the שליח *shaliach*, it still belongs to the משלח *meshaleach*
and he gets half the profit but he doesn't suffer the loss
because of it's the שליח *shaliach*'s fault, but it still belongs to
the משלח *meshaleach*. And the challenge here is if this is considered
to be a real שינוי *shinui*, a real violation of the wishes,
then why is it that the original sender now owns the wheat
or barley? Okay, but we and and what's being challenged now is
the question about well why is it that way even if he's
doing the will of the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis*, isn't it necessary
that the seller has to know that it's going to the משלח
*meshaleach*? And that's what's being questioned now. So if the seller does
know and even in the case when he's doing the right thing,
when he's buying told wheat and bought wheat the seller knows that
it has that it's going to the משלח *meshaleach* and the שליח
*shaliach* is informing him I'm representing Mr. Jones and the seller has
intent to give it to Mr. Jones, then that can also be
our answer when there's a violation, even when there's a violation the
seller is intending that the barley go to Mr. Jones. The seller
doesn't know there's a violation. So as long so if you explain
the whole case that the seller has been informed that it's for
Mr. Jones, we have an answer to our question. Then whether he's
doing the right thing or not doing the right thing the seller
intends to transfer the wheat or the barley to Mr. Jones. Okay
and that everything works smoothly. However if the seller doesn't know then
the גמרא *Gemara* is stuck because then we understand why it works
when the שליח *shaliach* is doing the right thing but we don't
understand why it works when the שליח *shaliach* is doing the wrong
thing. Okay we will stop here for now.